{"tossups": [{"question": "The \u201csalmon argument\u201d was support for a now discredited hypothesis for locating this place. An eastern boundary for where this place could have been is set by the natural distribution of honey bees. A 2015 study by Haak et al found high genetic similarity between the people of the Yamnaya and Corded Ware Cultures, supporting the most accepted theory for the location of this place. Borrowed words for \u201cto give\u201d, \u201cto walk\u201d, and \u201cto wash\u201d in Proto-Uralic have been used to locate this place. The ability to reconstruct words for (*) wheeled transport supports Marija Gimbutas\u2019 Kurgan Hypothesis, which designates the Pontic-Caspian steppes of Ukraine and Russia as this place. For 10 points, name this place where the first common ancestor of languages like Hindi, Russian, Latin, and English was spoken.", "answer": "Indo-European homeland or Indo-European urheimat (accept descriptive answers that convey that it\u2019s the place where Proto-Indo-European was spoken)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The most recent independent government to rule from this city was installed with the military prowess of G\u00fcshi Khan who defeated the Kham Kingdom and successfully besieged Shigatse. A riot in this city in 1750 began after the ambans Labdon and Fucin assassinated a prince, leading to the installation of the Kashag council. A palace in this city was constructed on Red Hill over a previous palace and is named after the home of Avalokite\u015bvara. This city first became a capital after the defeat of the Zhangzhung Kingdom by (*) Songtsen Gampo. The Ganden Phodrang was a government that ruled from this city that until a 1959 revolt against China drove its leader into exile in India. For 10 points, what is this former seat of the Dalai Lama and the capital of Tibet?", "answer": "Lhasa", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One ruler of this country started life as a pig farmer and rose to power by leading a peasant army against the Mongols. That man was Ivailo the Cabbage. A defensive line in this country ran through Vitosha and followed the Rhodope Mountains. This modern country was the target of the Savoyard Crusade. The people who name this country had a state at the confluence of the Volga and Kama Rivers before moving to their more notable homeland. The city of (*) Tarnovo in this country was the capital of an empire named for this country and was called a Third Rome. The people of this country were famously defeated at the Battle of Kleidion where 99 of 100 of the losers were blinded. For 10 points, identify this Balkan country currently governed from Sofia.", "answer": "Bulgaria", "category": "History"}, {"question": "After joining with Manapa-Tarhunta in a failed rebellion, the last king of a state in this modern country, Uhha-Ziti, fled to a land known locally as Ahhiyawa. The Dorak Affair was a scandal in which archaeologist James Mellaart was accused of selling antiquities from a famous site in this country. Two prominent theories for the origin of the most famous ancient people of this country relate them to the Ezero culture of the Balkans or the Maikop culture of the Caucasus and they referred to two regions to the west collectively as (*) Luwia. The Paphlagonian city of Sinope was founded by Miletus in this country. The region of Phrygia in this modern country was home to the Gordian Knot and King Midas. For 10 points, what is this modern country home to the ruins of \u00c7atalh\u00f6y\u00fck and Troy?", "answer": "Republic of Turkey (reluctantly take Anatolia despite the exclusive use of the pronoun \u201ccountry\u201d)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A porn star in Frank Miller\u2019s Batman: The Dark Knight Returns is named after this event and in another comic that character claims to be the dictator of Ohio. Slavoj \u017di\u017eek defended a film depiction of this event against claims that it supported American intervention in the Middle East. Gun rights activists in America have used the quote \u201cMolon labe\u201d, originally given prior to this event, to defend their cause. A film about this event was criticized as being \u201c(*) anti-disability\u201d for making a historical person into a hunchback who reveals a secret path to an enemy force. This event is parodied in an episode of South Park where the Les Bos bar is nearly purchased by Iranians before Mrs. Garrison seduces their leader, Rauf Xerxes. For 10 points, name this 480 BCE battle featuring the 300 Spartans.", "answer": "Battle of Thermopylae", "category": "History"}, {"question": "An army of this people was reportedly massacred after their enemy purposely allowed them to capture a banquet, leading that army to get wasted on wine, which they had never experienced before. Some scholars link this people to a similarly named group from the Balkans based on an Avestan prefix for \u201cgreat\u201d or \u201cstrong\u201d in their name. A prince of this people, Spargapises, killed himself after being released from captivity upon learning of a defeat at the hands of Croesus. A queen of this people allegedly placed the (*) severed head of a defeated king into a wineskin with human blood to sate that king\u2019s bloodlust. This people successfully fended off the Persians under the leadership of Queen Tomyris. For 10 points, name this Iranian people, most famous for killing Cyrus the Great.", "answer": "Massagetae", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Walter, Baron von Richthofen, uncle of the Red Baron, wrote an influential tract popularizing this industry in the late 19th century. A gift from George Vancouver to King Kamehameha I was the impetus for the start of this industry in Hawaii, where it was carried out by paniolos. The Johnson County War was fought between large and small scale producers in this industry. (*) Charles Goodnight first brought this industry in a large-scale to the Texas Panhandle. The winter of 1886-87 saw some producers in this industry lose 90% of their investment, a catastrophe called the Great Die Up. Joseph Glidden\u2019s 1874 patent of barbed wire led to the demise of the open range variety of this industry. For 10 points, this is what industry that raises bovines for their meat?", "answer": "cattle ranching (accept answers that suggest that cows are being raised for meat; prompt on partial answer; do not accept or prompt on dairy farming)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In 1985, this city signed a peace treaty sent by an ancient enemy to officially end a war begun over 2,000 years earlier. An expedition led by a man from this city may have been the first people from the Mediterranean to see gorillas as it traveled to the coast of modern Gabon. Rome founded Colonia Junonia on the site of this city, though that may have been sabotaged by an earlier Roman action at the site. This city was governed by a council known as the (*) Hundred and Four and had power over magistrates called shophets. This city had two harbors, one for merchant ships and the other for military ships. A hill called the Byrsa was where the founder of this city was apocryphally given an ox hide\u2019s worth of land. For 10 points, name this city where the Romans salted the earth and that Cato the Elder said \u201cmust be destroyed\u201d.", "answer": "Carthage", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Study of this document by the Ahnenerbe was cancelled due to the onset of WWII. This document records that upon his defeat, the rebel Phraortes had his nose, ears, tongue, and an eye removed and was displayed in chains outside the palace before being crucified. This document describes a river crossing made on horses, camels, and inflated skins to attack the army of Nidintu-Bel. This document justifies the position of the ruler who ordered it created by claiming that he saved the kingdom from the possibly fictional usurper (*) Gaumata. That ruler who had this inscription created was a lance-bearer for a previous king and rose to power after killing Bardiya. This inscription says that anyone who destroys it will be smote by Ahura Mazda. For 10 points, this is what inscription detailing the exploits of Darius I that was crucial in the decipherment of cuneiform?", "answer": "Behistun Inscription (accept Bisutun, Bisotun, Bagastana, or Bistun)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This region was the birthplace of Locusta the Poisoner, a woman who founded a poisoner\u2019s school in Rome and killed Claudius with a poisoned feather. One city on the south coast of this region was founded by colonists from Phocaea around 600 BCE, and that city was later the home to the navigator Pytheas. The Battle of Magetobriga was fought between tribes in this region, leading the losers, the Aedui, to seek aid from Rome. The Rock of the Wyvern was a hill containing an artisan neighborhood in the city of (*) Bibracte in this province. A section of this region was led by Syagrius and was the last rump state of the Western Roman Empire. This region came under the rule of Rome after the defeat of Vercingetorix. For 10 points, what is this region comprising modern Switzerland, the Low Countries, and France?", "answer": "Gaul (accept Gallia or Gallia Lugdunensis/Narbonensis/Aquitania/Belgica)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One king of this city was supposedly single-handedly captured by Dumuzid the Fisherman and is recorded constructing the first temple to Enlil in the Tummal Inscription. Aga, a king of this city, was the final member of this city\u2019s First Dynasty and besieged Uruk. Due to its strategic location, rulers of nearby cities often styled themselves \u201cKing of [this city]\u201d instead of their home city upon conquering it as a symbol of their power. Kugbau, the grandmother of a famous ruler of this city and one-time alewife, is the first known woman to rule in her own name in Mesopotamia. King (*) Enmebaragesi of this city was jokingly made into a woman in The Epic of Gilgamesh and is this city\u2019s first archaeologically verified ruler. For 10 points, this is what city of northern Sumer, whose king Ur-Zababa employed Sargon I as cupbearer?", "answer": "Kish", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One side in a battle fought in this colony evacuated the \u201cFort of Young Saplings\u201d due to a lack of gunpowder, allowing the victors to establish what would become the capital of this colony. A statesman from this colony became engaged to Concepci\u00f3n Arg\u00fcello, the daughter of the man who founded Los Angeles, while on a trade mission for badly needed food. The crew of a ship belonging to a company named after this colony was temporarily enslaved by the Makah people on the Olympic Peninsula until rescued by the American merchant ship Lydia, though that company had a more famous attempt at southern expansion with the establishment of (*) Fort Elizabeth on Kaua\u2019i. The Tlingit claimed that the only land this colony\u2019s owners were truly in possession of was Castle Hill in Sitka following its transfer to a new owner. For 10 points, name this colony bought for $7.2 million by America in 1867.", "answer": "Russian America (or Russian Alaska; prompt on Alaska)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "ANSWER: Russian America (or Russian Alaska; prompt on Alaska)  13. The political dominance of a subset of this group was called \u201csedo\u201d, or \u201cin-law\u201d, politics during the reign of a child monarch in the early 19th century. Membership in this group could be revoked if a family failed to produce a government official for three consecutive generations. A group of people categorically excluded from this class are thought dirty due to their increased contact with meat and are believed to be the descendants of (*) Khitan immigrants. Jokbos were commonly used to prove one\u2019s membership in this class. These people were allowed to attend schools called seowon in preparation for the gwageo examination and lasted until the 1894 Gabo Reforms, a response to the Donghak Rebellion. For 10 points, what was this aristocratic class of Joseon Korea?", "answer": "yangban (prompt on descriptive answers)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The first labor strike in the Americas was led by people of this ethnic group in 1619 because they were prohibited from voting in Virginia. The Great Emigration led to some of these people moving to the US. The first major wave of immigration of people of this ethnicity was called \u201cZa khlebem\u201d, or \u201cFor Bread\u201d, due to the large numbers of poor farmers involved. One of the most famous (*) of these people was a member of the szlachta called \u201cthe father of American cavalry\u201d and died at the Battle of Savannah. For 10 points, identify these people who have included Casimir Pu\u0142aski, Zbigniew Brzezinski, and Tadeusz Kosciusko.", "answer": "Polish-Americans (accept any answer that suggests people of Polish descent; reluctantly take Polacks)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The rice-growing Ledwin region was this kingdom\u2019s economic center. The first origin story for this kingdom claimed that its founder was the son of a dragon and a solar spirit, but was later replaced by the account given in the Glass Palace Chronicle. This kingdom emerged from the Pyu city-states and its capital had a Pali name meaning \u201ccity that tramples on enemies\u201d. The most famous ruler of this kingdom converted it to Theravada Buddhism from Ari Buddhism and received a replica of one of the Buddha\u2019s teeth as thanks for helping repulse a Chola invasion of Sri Lanka. This kingdom originated a council of advisors that developed into the legislature of its modern successor, the (*) Hluttaw. This kingdom\u2019s political rise began in the 11th century under King Anawrahta and soon expanded from its heartland in the Irrawaddy River valley. For 10 points, name this medieval Burmese kingdom.", "answer": "Kingdom/Empire of Pagan (accept Bagan Kingdom)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The daughter of a de facto ruler of this state offered to marry anyone who could best her in a wrestling match and had them give her 100 horses if they lost, leading to her supposedly winning 10,000 horses. A rump state of this polity was based at Yarkent and lasted until the early 18th century Advised by his daughter Khutulun, the warlord Kaidu took effective command of this state and appointed Duwa as its official leader, under whom this state reached its greatest extent. Babur\u2019s autobiography, the (*) Baburnama, was written in a language named after the first ruler of this state. The founder of this state was the first to oversee the Yassa system and was the brother of Tolui, Jochi, and \u00d6gedei. For 10 points, identify this khanate that ruled much of Central Asia until the rise of Timur.", "answer": "Chagatai Khanate", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This battle\u2019s winner had earlier assassinated Count Andeiro, leading merchants in his future capital to claim him \u201crector and defender of the realm\u201d. Following this battle, the \u201cBaker-woman of [this battle\u2019s location]\u201d apocryphally killed 8 men hiding in her bakery. The defending army in this engagement borrowed English tactics when they fortified the south side of a hill with ditches and caltrops. The winners of this battle had flanks called the \u201cAla de Namorados\u201d and \u201cAla de Madressilva\u201d, or the (*) \u201cLover\u2019s Flank\u201d and \u201cHoneysuckle\u2019s Flank\u201d. The victor of this battle defended a claim to a throne gained from marrying Princess Beatrice with troops drawn from Braga and Guimar\u00e3es. Fought in 1385 between John I of Castile and John I of Portugal, for 10 points, name this battle which established the Aviz Dynasty as the ruling house of Portugal.", "answer": "Battle of Aljubarrota", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Descriptive answer acceptable Part of this process granted free land to veterans of a recent war, an action that was forcibly bankrolled by the livery companies of the City of London. A leader of those veterans also exiled 1,300 soldiers of the region affected to Sweden. Important landholders in this process were called \u201cUndertakers\u201d and were required to import laborers from nearby lands. The failure of the Desmond Rebellions contributed to this process. This process was begun soon after the (*) Flight of the Earls drained much of the region in question\u2019s leadership and was most successful in the counties of Munster and Ulster. Shortly following Tyrone\u2019s Rebellion, for 10 points, what was this 17th century process that brought Protestantism and English settlers to \u201ccivilize\u201d the second largest British Isle?", "answer": "Plantation of Ireland (accept answers that say that the English are settling/colonizing Ireland; accept Plantation of Ulster/equivalents as the first two clues are about the Anglicization of that region)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Nikolai Notovich claimed that he had found evidence of Jesus travelling to this country in the Hemis Monastery, but confessed to making up the story after attracting due scholarly criticism. The Cuncolim Revolt was a reaction against the imposition of Christianity in a colony in this country. The largest community of Christians in this country is split between the Northists and Southists over who first brought the religion here. The man most widely credited with bringing Christianity to this country has a tomb in the city where he died on the (*) Coromandel Coast. Christianity was one of the religions included in discussions at the Ib\u0101dat Kh\u0101na under the founder of the syncretic religion D\u012bn-i Il\u0101h\u012b, a ruler whose abolition of the jizya was reversed by a future emperor, Aurangzeb. For 10 points, name this country where Christianity was supposedly first brought by St. Thomas the Apostle to Kerala.", "answer": "India", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Dale Kerwin claims that a group of trackers was denied reentry into their homeland after serving in the Second Boer War due to this policy. The extremely difficult Stewart test became the standard means of enforcing this policy. A supporter of this policy claimed it would stop the \u201cveiled slavery\u201d of Kanakas. The spirit of this policy is alive today in Pauline Hanson\u2019s (*) One Nation Party. Because this policy forbade the import of low-wage Pacific Islanders, sugar planters in Queensland strongly opposed this policy. Egon Kisch was denied entry into the country enacting this policy because he was Jewish. For 10 points, name this policy that sought to prevent immigration to the land Down Under from outside Anglophone countries.", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}